Was not
Thanks.
kylie jue: So the vase is not equal to a. So, suppose your baseless Jeep. It wasn't equal to a. This whole esteem, it will still evaluate to true. Because what happens is you're just saying, or this character and c++ just treats a random character.
kylie jue: As a, as a true value because it's not sort of like like a string basically treated as a true value because it's just sort of a
kylie jue: Feature or a bug in c++
kylie jue: So you want to make sure that you are having two separate conditions here, not just separating the or even though this would seem like the correct way to do it. If you spoke said it in English and spoken language.
kylie jue: You have to have this base equals equals twice because of order of operations.
kylie jue: And then another thing NC in CS one of 16 which is a little bit different. If you are in 106 a we're going to ask you to add include statements yourself. One thing I know when
kylie jue: In 106 say is common. If you don't see the import statement already there, sometimes you're like, Oh, is that a tip that I'm not doing the right thing because they didn't include that library.
kylie jue: That's not the case for 160 and I just want to emphasize that we want you to be including your own libraries. And so we won't always include everything that you need in those files.
kylie jue: So if you tried to use either of these two functions to upper on characters or to uppercase on strings you needed to include their respective libraries.
kylie jue: Alright, so that's a little bit about the DNA exercises and some of the things the common
kylie jue: Bugs are things that we saw. We went over abstract data types last time, which are powerful abstractions to allow programmers to store data in structured and organized ways
kylie jue: And 80s, in particular, give us guarantees about the organization and properties of the data. Well, we don't have to worry about how its implemented underneath.
kylie jue: And we're going to study specific implementations of a DTS based on the Stanford C c++ libraries that we're providing to you, but you'll see these
kylie jue: General abstractions for data structures transcending language boundaries so across Java and Python and other languages, you might encounter.
kylie jue: And then just another term I wanted to throw out at TS provide interfaces for data storage that programmers can use without needing to understand the underlying implementation.
kylie jue: And this again goes back to this idea of an abstraction boundary where the interface or the ADT itself is sort of defining what that boundary is between the programmer and the person who created the data structure.
kylie jue: Alright, so we learned about our first ADT which is actually also an ordered data structure factories and it's ordered because it stores them in a particular order with indices that allow you to access
kylie jue: Different elements inside of the collection. Unlike other languages all elements in this in a vector and c++ need to be the same type.
kylie jue: And vectors are flexible in terms of the number of elements that can store you can just keep adding to them as well as removing them and then vectors will automatically update what size they are based on that.
kylie jue: We also learned about references because we talked about how when you pass a vector into a function, you often want to use pass by reference. And we'll talk a little about why
kylie jue: But again references you can think about it, it's just like the square that points to an actual variable. So,
kylie jue: They also have names and they also have types, but to indicate that it's a reference you put this ampersand after the type to say that it's a reference to a particular type rather than the actual type itself.
kylie jue: So when do we use them. We use them with our helper functions or in functions where we want to edit data structures inside of that function.
kylie jue: Instead of creating an entire copy of the data structure because if we pass it by value and returned the data structure, we would be making a copy often have a very large data structure in memory, which reduces the efficiency of our code.
kylie jue: We also talked briefly about multiple return values.
kylie jue: Basically references allow you to
kylie jue: Edit Multiple things and return are basically returned different things you can have like a return statement that's actually returning one thing and then you're also editing the data structure that you passed in. So, sort of, in a way, you're returning in quotation marks.
kylie jue: Two different things. And don't worry if this last point is still a little bit confusing or not totally clear for you. We're going to get a lot more practice with that when we get later in the quarter, but you won't have to worry about that on this next assignment yet.
kylie jue: It'll become more prominent when we go over new topics and we'll review it again. Then, so just to get us warmed up as a review from last time. And since I know we went over references pretty quickly last class. We're going to do some five, a quick five minute breakout room.
kylie jue: With a trace problem. And just to show you what this looks like. So we're going to put you in breakout rooms again in Ed. And what you're going to do. There's instructions here.
kylie jue: But basically, introduce yourself to your group mates. I just wanted to reiterate this say your name, your preferred pronouns and just one fun fact about yourself.
kylie jue: And then what you're going to do is you're going to read through this code and rather than running it. What we want you to do is fill in.
kylie jue: What you think the values are what what is a look like and what does a B look like at each point where we have this to do
kylie jue: So this is again a trace problem where you're just reading through the code and trying to figure out what happens
kylie jue: And then once you've guessed, go ahead and you can go ahead and run it and we'll go over the answers when you come back as well. But this is just to give you some practice with pass by reference and parameter passing in general in c++
kylie jue: Ah okay I'm gonna have to open the breakout rooms. Give me one second.
kylie jue: While I'm doing this. I'm gonna leave this code open like this for you to look at so that you can get familiar with it, as I'm doing the breakout rooms.
kylie jue: Um,
Let's see.
Alright.
kylie jue: Create breakout rooms and then I'm gonna stop the countdown to 10 and I'm actually just for the sake of time, I'll give you five minutes up okay um
kylie jue: Alright, and I've opened rooms now.
kylie jue: Go ahead and join and go to the room with your number.
Would you say, You're welcome.
All right, Nick. I've made you the host
kylie jue: Yeah. So for those of you who are watching not or not live or for some reason are not able to join a breakout room. I'm going to go ahead and walk through what's going on in this exercise here.
kylie jue: And you'll also be able to take a look on Ed after this. So we have a vector A that stores the integers one zero and six, and we have a vector B, which has negative five, four, negative one and seven.
kylie jue: And then we have three functions we have a function called Saki a function called Buster and a function called Lola, which Fun fact or the name of our pets.
kylie jue: So what we have here is
kylie jue: Saki is going to take in a vector and then remove the elements until the size
kylie jue: Is until it basically has removed all of the items inside of the vector. And then it's going to return it. But one thing to notice here is that
kylie jue: Psaki is actually getting called but the value that is getting returned is not being stored and since this is not being passed by reference.
kylie jue: What happens is this vector A, that you're passing just stays the same. It may be modified inside of this function but nothing's going to happen to it out here.
kylie jue: So I'll show the values in a moment in buster. Here we are passing in the vector p. So, this is the first time we're using the vector beat and this time we are passing by reference. So basically anything that we do to the vector be inside of this function is going to
kylie jue: Happen to the vector be outside of this function or where it's called over here as well. So in here, all we're doing with this for loop is we're iterating over the elements inside and then negating them.
kylie jue: And so what will happen out here is be all these signs are basically going to get flipped. So the answers to A and B here.
kylie jue: Are a and b won't change for this first to do and for the second to do
kylie jue: A won't change you're not doing anything to it and then be you'll see all of these signs flipped. And then the last one, Lola takes in both of our vectors and be so far. So keep in mind this is be with the science flipped and then regular a
kylie jue: And so what you're doing here is you're passing be in by reference and a you are not passing
Andrew Shin: By reference
kylie jue: And so what happens is we are storing we're making a copy of A and storing inside of a temporary variable.
kylie jue: And then we're assigning a equal to the vector be and resigning be able to temp and then we're adding
kylie jue: A team to be so when we signed up to temp we're assigning be to remember it was the original value of a
kylie jue: So be becomes the vector A, and then you add 18 to it. And remember the vector is 106. So what you end up without here is
kylie jue: Again, because a was passed was passed by value. So copy was made, nothing's going to happen to the vector A, but the vector be what happens is you end up with 106 and then 18 at the and I'll show that in a second when people return from breakout rooms. When I run this code.
kylie jue: And then the other thing I just wanted to make a note of this is something that is sort of
kylie jue: mentioned a lot and want to succeed, but just as a reminder, is that, again, these value. We've made the names of these variables, the same inside and outside just to make it super clear with this trace problem what's going on.
kylie jue: But I could have called this be and this A and then swapped all the word the names in here and it would have had the same effect basically these the name a and the name a out here doesn't mean that the to have to be related
kylie jue: You can sort. It's poor style. If they're not, but just a note that that is not why like if I swapped the values of these two parameters.
kylie jue: It will do something different inside of Lola and you can experiment with that on your own. But that's just something I wanted to point out in terms of understanding. I think it's about time to bring people back. Alright, sweet.
kylie jue: All right. Alright, well,
kylie jue: People are coming back.
kylie jue: I'm going to go ahead and do this.
kylie jue: I'm going to start adding in these print statements. So we can see the answers to our problem.
kylie jue: So for this first one.
kylie jue: If I opened the terminal.
And hit me run
kylie jue: What we see here is just after this function Saki gets called basically nothing changes about these. And the reason for that is that even though we pass in a
kylie jue: To the function we're not passing it by reference. So any changes that happened to the vector A inside of here are not going to persist outside of the function. So the answer to this first one is that neither of them change.
kylie jue: And then here, if I go to Buster, what's going to happen.
kylie jue: And this case again isn't training because we're not editing a but be what happens is the changes do persist and the changes are just that we're flipping the sign. So all of the negative numbers become positive and vice versa.
kylie jue: And because we're passing it in by reference the changes that are happening inside of the function Buster are going to persist.
kylie jue: And then for the last one.
kylie jue: After Lola.
kylie jue: What we have is again a isn't going to change, but be becomes 106 18 and again the reason for that. If you look up at Lola.
kylie jue: The second parameter here is being passed by reference. So anything that happens to be will persist. Anything that happens to a because it's passed by value will not and what we're doing inside here is we're basically setting be equal to the original values of a and then adding at
kylie jue: All right.
kylie jue: And feel free to if you have more questions about this, like, take this code and test it out yourself and make some changes to see what happens when you change what's pass by reference when you change the names of variables or the operations, you're doing
kylie jue: It's a great way to just sort of better understand how pass by references working
kylie jue: Alright.
kylie jue: So with that, I'm going to go ahead and move on to the new content for today. So we're going to talk about ordered data structures.
kylie jue: And when we talk about order data structures. That's just to say that the data that's being stored inside maintains a particular order.
kylie jue: So the first one is grids and grids are pretty similar to vectors. What is a grid grid as a 2D or a defined with a particular with them height. So in this case we have a three by three grid.
kylie jue: And I'm using the word array here instead of actor, just because the
kylie jue: Dimensions get established one the greatest creative with the vector, you can keep adding things and you can make it smaller and larger as you're working with it.
kylie jue: But when you define the grid you have to tell the grid what dimensions, it is you are able to resize it in c++ but it's a specific call to resize to like actually set the dimensions.
kylie jue: What are grids useful for their useful for spreadsheets game boards, etc. And there are three different ways to create a grid that I'm going to talk about the first one here is when you just say grid which is the type
kylie jue: Of the variable you give it a type. So this could be
kylie jue: Into character string anything and then the name of your variable, the grid name.
kylie jue: And this is just going to, by default, create an empty grid. So if size zero. So nothing inside of it. And then you will have to resize it and assign values in order to do anything with it.
kylie jue: You could also just reassign it. So once you've created it like this, you could say board equals, and I'll show you in a second what that looks like.
kylie jue: Like with curly brackets, you could define the grid that way. But basically, if you declare declare a grid. This way before you use it, you need to either resize it or via assignment.
kylie jue: The second way to create a grid is to set the number of rows and columns right when you declare it like this. So in this case, it looks almost exactly the same except now you have three three, and that would create this three by three grid.
kylie jue: And initialize all of the values inside to a default value depending on the type and you can again experiment with the different types of see what those default values turn to in the case of its they're all going to default to zero inside and you would have to index like this where
kylie jue: This is the row and this is the column.
Demi Lei: In order to assign particular values.
kylie jue: All right. And then we have the third way of creating a grid which was what I was referring to when I was talking about the first
kylie jue: One where you can just set it.
kylie jue: Equal to and then you use these curly bracket notation is to actually denote the rows and columns. And so what you would say is the name again type and then the name of the grid. And then you have this would be the first row and this would be the second row.
Demi Lei: Alright.
kylie jue: So those are the three ways to declare a grid, you can do it, depending on what you're using the grid for you can decide which one best suits your needs.
kylie jue: And then just a side note here because I know this question might come up. We could use a combination of vectors to simulate A to D matrix, but a grid tends to be easier here and there's actually benefits to having this constraint width and height and needing to resize
kylie jue: As opposed to having these variable size.
kylie jue: Presenters nested
kylie jue: Within one another. It's just a little bit cleaner to use a
Grid in this case.
kylie jue: Some important grid methods.
kylie jue: So,
kylie jue: Numb rows and numb calls columns so grid.
kylie jue: The grid knows how many rows and columns. It has and allows you to
kylie jue: Select specific elements using the I throw in the Jade column. So again, this
kylie jue: First index will always refer to the
kylie jue: Row. The second index will always refer to the column.
kylie jue: You can resize the grid like I showed
kylie jue: And then there's also this really handy function for things that are in balance. So you can see if you've given a row or column that is out of balance of your actual grid size, it'll return false.
kylie jue: And these three in particular are going to be very useful when you move on to assignment to which is coming out later this week.
kylie jue: Another just quick side note, related to this, but also just more generally about documentation. So this is, again, not all of the grid methods that are possible. There are more grid methods mentioned in the Stanford documentation here.
kylie jue: And I just wanted to make a note, more generally about documentation is that
kylie jue: The reason documentation exists is that we don't expect you to memorize absolutely everything about grids and we don't even do that ourselves. So reading and understanding documentation is a really important part of programming and something that you will do if you
kylie jue: Work in an engineering job and practice.
kylie jue: So we want you to get practice with actually reading and going through documentation and understanding it will often cover the main like things you need to know to get started here.
kylie jue: But we definitely encourage you to check out the documentation. When you have a question like, can I do this with a grid or it does this function exist.
kylie jue: often will say, go look at the documentation, because again we don't expect you to memorize that. And it's a good practice to have as a programmer.
Alright.
kylie jue: How to traverse a grid. So in other words, how to go through a grid. So this is a common
kylie jue: Pattern that you'll see for going through a grid.
kylie jue: Is you will have a double for loop and then you iterate over the rows and columns. It doesn't really matter which one's the outer versus the inner one you can switch them as long as you make sure these indices are correct when you're indexing into the grid here.
kylie jue: And so then the rose. Remember will be this first one in the columns at the second one and you just double for loop over and this one is just printing out each of the items in the grid.
kylie jue: So if we can do a quick poll. Just about that. What do you think the output of this function is going to be, is it a he. Haha, a
kylie jue: Yea, I can't even pronounce all of these, but you can see them on the side here. He hw on the second line is it going to break the lines after each row like this or is it none of the above.
kylie jue: So pay attention to the line breaks there and go ahead and make your guesses.
kylie jue: And Nick, if you could tell me when we're about 85% in
You can see it.
kylie jue: I cannot. No.
kylie jue: Okay, great.
kylie jue: Cool.
kylie jue: Alright, so
kylie jue: Nice, there's a pretty good split between A and C and then some for D and B, but that one was a little. Those are a little less popular. So let's go ahead and walk through it and see what happens. So
kylie jue: We have our variables which are starting at zero in our for loops and we're going to go ahead and put the output here. So when R and C are both equal to zero. So the first time you go into these nested for loops, you're going to get the why.
kylie jue: And then you have see going up by one and that's when you're going to get the E. And so now here's the key part right when you have now. See, it's going to go up to two
kylie jue: That is going to break out of this inner for loop, right, because when see is too, it is no longer less than the number of columns which is two.
kylie jue: And then it's going to come out and go to this see out. Remember this is inside this outer for loop, but outside of this inner folio. And so what that does is it'll insert a line break here and then the next time you go through, you have an E
kylie jue: And an H and this is what the our value equal to one. And again, once you get to see equals to you'll come out here. And so you see the pattern here. So the correct answer. There was see
kylie jue: Cool. So that's just a little bit of a caveat of thinking about where you want to actually put your line breaks and different print statements, when you have nested for loops to determine what you want the output to look like when you print it.
kylie jue: Alright, common pitfalls when using grid so common bugs that we see or errors that we, that are made. Don't forget to specify what data type is stored in your grid.
kylie jue: Especially because I know data types. In general, if you're coming from Python or new um, you have to indicate what you're storing inside of the grid. So you would do something like this.
kylie jue: Don't just do it like that. That'll give you an air in c++ and like vectors and a DTS grids should be passed by reference when they're used as function parameters and you want to be editing them between your functions.
kylie jue: And then, like I mentioned, watch the variable ordering with their grid indices, it's often more intuitive to use our and see for row and column as opposed to I and J. When your indexing in because that's where you can run into bugs. If you don't have the right size for your grid.
kylie jue: And then. Unlike in other languages. You can only access cells, not individual rose. I know. I think in Python, and in Java. If you're doing nested data structures in order to create a 2D array or a grid. You can often do something like this. I know that bars popping up.
kylie jue: To just get like the first row of the grid. You can't do that in c++ you can only access specific cells.
kylie jue: Alright, so before I oh before I go on to this example. Are there any questions about grids anything in the chat. Nick, that I should answer.
kylie jue: Okay, anyone who would like to just. Is there anything if anyone would like to raise their hand and say or ask about grits before. Yeah.
Kaan Alp Yay: Yeah. Is this a c++ standard type or is this a. Is this a Stanford library specific type
kylie jue: Yeah, this is a Stanford library specific type
Kaan Alp Yay: Thank you.
Any other questions.
yukun yang: That's a step of every specific type
yukun yang: O, which what we need to include in the beginning of this coat, then
kylie jue: Oh yes, that's a good question. Um, I don't think I might not have put it in. So it will be if you actually here, I can just type it into the workspace at the top to show you it's going to look like this include
kylie jue: And then grid dot h like this. And anytime at the Stanford library specific you'll see these quotation marks. So it'll look like that. You can also, if you go to the documentation. It says what to include at the very top of the documentation link that's in the slide a few back. Yeah.
sidharth bhat: Okay. All right. I also want to ask up
sidharth bhat: Is so this is treated like a grid, but is there a difference between this and sort of using like a vector within a vector.
kylie jue: Yeah. So again, the vector within a vector, there will be no constraints about like
kylie jue: So, for example, with a grid.
kylie jue: Right, if you have something that looks like this.
kylie jue: Every row will be a link to with some default values in there, even if you haven't populated it yet.
kylie jue: If you have vectors within a vector, you might have one row. The first vectors only linked one and the second one is linked to and there won't be these it won't have this sort of uniform structure to it so it won't look like a perfect rectangle. If you're using nested vectors. Yeah.
sidharth bhat: What practically used to be able to make a grid outside of the standard library.
kylie jue: Yeah, so we're going to talk about something called arrays.
kylie jue: Later in the quarter. When we move to the other side of the abstraction boundary. And that's why I sort of when I was defining the grids. Originally I talked about this term of a 2D array. So that's going to be something that we're going to talk about later.
kylie jue: Cool, yeah.
kylie jue: Alright, so I'm going to go ahead and just show an example of like why are
kylie jue: Or this is actually going to, it's going to lead into the next topic, but so for example if any of you've ever played the game battleship
kylie jue: Battleship is a game where you are playing against an opponent and you have ships and you basically call out things like d two and you want to try to hit the other opponents ships and you take turns doing that.
kylie jue: But basically you put your ships along this grid. And so it would be really useful in a
kylie jue: Website version or an online version of this to actually use a grid to store information about where your ships are
kylie jue: And so this is an example, usually on a in the actual board game you have numbers and the letters here so it's easier to call them out.
kylie jue: But you could imagine that if you're doing this in programming, you would have you would need to have indices. So it would go from zero to eight and then zero to eight over here.
kylie jue: But one question I want to pose is what would we do if we want to keep track of all the cells. Worship is present. Right. So if you're playing a game.
kylie jue: Of battleship online. You can imagine that when someone says out a cell, and they want to try to see if a ship is there your program just needs to keep track of all the cells in your grid where our ship, ship is present to say yes, you hit it, or no, you did it.
kylie jue: And in practice, it's not that easy to do, right, if you think about how a greatest stored, you'd have to store all of these like all of the rows that correspond to all of the columns, there's no way to sort of group, the cell information together.
kylie jue: Until now, so we're going to talk about something called a struct. I'm in particular in the Stanford c++ libraries. There's a predefined structure called grid location. So what is a struct.
kylie jue: A struct is a way to bundle different types of information in c++ kind of like creating a custom data structure.
kylie jue: So as an example, the grid location struct will allow you to store both a row and column index together in one data type.
kylie jue: And so this is again a predefined structure in the Stanford c++ libraries that looks exactly like this. So when you define a struct in c++
kylie jue: You use this keyword struct. You give it a name and then you say, all of these things inside and these are called the members inside. So you give it a type and then the name of that type. I mean, in particular with grid locations. We just have our grouping together a row in a column index.
kylie jue: And so to declare a struct. You can either assign each of its members separately.
kylie jue: Or assign it when it gets created. So we've created this is the definition of a structure behind the scenes. And when you actually use a grid location struck you could do something like this.
kylie jue: Grid location origin is equal to, and we still use these curly brackets and this will just go in order of how you define them here. So this first one will be the row and the second one will be the column.
kylie jue: Alternatively, you could do grid location origin and then use the dot notation to assign each of these members and you can just refer to each of the members by saying origin row origins column.
kylie jue: And if you had a different type of struck you do the same thing. It's just the names of the members inside here and you use that dot notation.
kylie jue: So you can access members in a struct using the dot notation. You don't remember one caveat is don't put the parentheses after because you're accessing a member. You're not calling a function. Those are different things and that's just a bug. I've seen come up before
kylie jue: And I'm pointing this out because this is sort of how the code looks different. If you're able to use a grid location structure as opposed to storing like basically two separate vectors, where you would have to store the row indices in the column column indices
kylie jue: This would be a lot messier and you'd have to then correspond based on the indexes in the vector that this is referring to one six and one seven right oh this sorry you should be zero, based on the indexes here.
kylie jue: I think it's all off by one because I adjust, but that's okay.
kylie jue: Versus in here. You could just store one vector of grid locations where each grid location has the role in the column grouped together. So again, what a structure. The takeaway from this a struct allows you to basically group pieces of information together.
kylie jue: When a normal c++ data type would not allow you to do that.
kylie jue: And as an exercise on your own. If you have the chance. I just think about how you would answer the question. Okay, suppose I am playing this game and I made this. And I said, Is there a ship at four three.
kylie jue: For each of these different ways of storing these the ship's, how would you have to figure that out. So if I asked the question, is there a ship it for three. How would you figure it out. If it was stored. This way versus how would you figure it out. If you are forced to store.
kylie jue: The cells. This way, and it's actually a lot harder to do it this way or a little more complicated.
kylie jue: Alright so yeah takeaways. This is the grid location structural see this come up. I'm mentioning it now because it comes up specifically on assignment to
kylie jue: And a common misconception is that grids are made up of grid location structure that's not true. The grid location instructors sort of the separate concept that just makes it really easy for you to store information about a specific
kylie jue: Cell in a grid both the role in the column or to store a series of like cells in terms of a particular order through a grid. The grid itself is still separate right like over here. You might have a grid of
kylie jue: A grid of Boolean telling you, true or false depending on whether or not a ship is present. That is a completely separate thing from the grid location struct, which would just allow you to store information about a particular cell. Alright.
kylie jue: I will make some quick let's I'm just looking at the time to see. Okay, so let's go ahead and do announcements. So a few quick announcements assignment. One is due tomorrow at 11:59pm in your time zone.
kylie jue: So that again. It's just depending on where you are. When your clock hits 1159 that's when your assignment is do
kylie jue: Check out our ED post answering your questions from the c++ survey. We tried to address them in the lecture last week, but we have a limited amount of time and there were a lot of questions.
kylie jue: So we addressed some of the other ones in this Ed post. We don't expect you to read the entire thing. But if you asked a question you didn't see enhancer. It might be there.
kylie jue: And it's also a good place to look for language specific differences we pulled those out into that post as well as a list of just general resources about c++
kylie jue: And one of 16 resources and then assignment two is going to be released by the end of the day, on Wednesday. So you get a little bit of a break between Assignment one and assignment to if you're not taking that grace period.
kylie jue: All right.
kylie jue: Before I move on. Any questions on the announcement, excuse me, or struck from the grid location struct before I go on to the next section of content.
Regina Ta: I have a question. When you write origin dot row equals zero or origin column. Do you need to highlight the data type like integers something for it.
kylie jue: So no, actually. So basically when you are declaring this struct over here it says you are going to have to put an integer into the row and an integer into the column. So once you say oh origin row equals this origin column equals this.
kylie jue: It's going to look for an integer here and c++ will detect will give you an error if you try to assign something different, but you don't have to. When you're using it, tell it that you're giving it an integer. Yeah.
Matt Presson: I've also got a question about
Matt Presson: Strikes. So are we going to be practicing creating structure in a separate file or early then same file or is there like a struct prototype, the same way as a function prototype.
kylie jue: Yeah, that's a good question. So you're actually you won't
Matt Presson: I'm
kylie jue: I bring obstructs now because you're going to be using the
kylie jue: Grid location struck on assignment to but we won't be asking you to create structure for at least another assignment or two.
kylie jue: So you won't need to worry about creating them yourself. And when we do get into creating them depending on what you're creating them for will let you know like do you need to create it in a specific file that's separate or just at the top, like a function prototype.
kylie jue: But that's a good question. Well, we'll let you know when we get to the part of actually asking you to create your own strokes.
Matt Presson: Thank you.
Matt Presson: Guys.
Kaan Alp Yay: Good question, to how destructive for from types or how is it different from objects. I guess I don't know what's
Kaan Alp Yay: Yeah right right question to ask. Yes, that's a good question.
kylie jue: So you get the way I would frame it as this structure, kind of like a way to create your own type
kylie jue: And will learn about classes. Later in the quarter classes are another way of also creating a new type structure of a little bit more of limited functionality than classes.
kylie jue: But so these are a little more succinct and for our purposes, we're just going to use them for grouping together pieces of information where classes will sort of allow you to have like functions associated with a new type of that sort of thing as well. Yeah, good question.
Kaan Alp Yay: Great, thank you.
Anything else
edouard des: Have a question. Um, is the current location only meant to contain a specific point. So, for instance, because we are talking about grouping multiple
edouard des: Points to form a ship and we still have to use multiple locations to create. So we'd have to some, but we could like make another grid, we could make another structure that's like ship made up of multiple grid locations and yeah, you could that so you'd have. Okay.
kylie jue: Yeah, the one thing they are right is the
kylie jue: hard thing is
kylie jue: If you're defining a ship. The reason it would actually maybe be better to something like a vector is you don't know how many grid locations, a ship is going to be made up of right and you'll notice in the structure, you have to sort of say exactly what
kylie jue: The things are in here versus over here like it's just easier to say I have a vector of many grid.
edouard des: Locations. That will be my ship.
edouard des: As opposed to saying like
kylie jue: My ship has exactly to grin locations and one is the beginning and oneness. The end or something like that. Yeah.
edouard des: Thank you.
edouard des: All right.
kylie jue: I'm going to go ahead and move on with the next couple data structure. So we have two more order data structures to get through in today's lecture. And they're often taught together and somewhat related. And so let's start with cues.
kylie jue: So a queue is like a real queue or line in real life. So you've probably all experienced waiting in line before the way they operate as the first person in. So the first person who started in the line will be the first person out to the first person to get helped
kylie jue: And so you'll hear these terms in Q AMP DQ in queue is adding someone into the line dQ is removing someone from the line when you remove someone from the queue. You remove them from the front of the line.
kylie jue: And then the last person in will be the last person served when you insert people again into the queue. You insert them at the back.
kylie jue: So again, just like a normal line would operate something you've seen in everyday life as well. So these are some methods.
kylie jue: In the Stanford c++ Q library. And again, just to clarify, again, both of these ones that I'm going to bring up our Stanford c++
kylie jue: They don't abstract data structures. So a Q has to implement at least the following functions. You have to be able to include something or add something to it. You have to be able to remove or DQ something peak allows you to look at the front of the queue without removing it and then
kylie jue: Is empty just basically as it returns a true or false value depending on if the queue is empty. And again, there's more. There are more functions there in the Stanford c++ documentation.
kylie jue: As an example, so this is how you would create a queue. So, similarly to what you saw with grids and vectors you say queue. And then the type that it's going to hold
kylie jue: As well as the name and then you can in-q values and it'll slowly fill the queue like this where this on the left hand side is the front
kylie jue: So when you DQ evaluate the first thing again. The first thing and will be the first thing out. We say FICO is the general convention their
kylie jue: First In First Out and 42 will come out and then you can peek without removing the element. And then if you DQ you'll actually remove the element.
kylie jue: So this is just an example. A simple example of how you would use a queue and practice. And you can also create a queue like this where you actually use the curly brackets right off the bat, if you know what you want your cue to be pre populated with
kylie jue: All right. Related is the data structure called a stack stack is again like the real world word a stack is like an actual stack maybe of pancakes, where the top element.
kylie jue: In the stack is what you can access. So the last item is the first one out. So you put all of them down. And then the last one that you put on the top will be the first one that you take off.
kylie jue: So the only operations that you can actually do want to stack are pushing which is adding something to the top popping which removes it from the top and then top which basically just allows you to look at the thing on the top. More specifically, these are the methods that we have
kylie jue: Again we have push your ad which purchase something on the top pop just like pops the top element off peak allows you to look at the top of the stack without removing it.
kylie jue: And is empty. Again, similar to cues. So you'll see very again these are very parallel structures with the stack versus the queue.
kylie jue: What we say with the stack is that it's lipo or last in first out versus the queue is FICO first in first out and then there's a link to documentation here.
kylie jue: And here's our stack example you can create a stack of strings and you would use push to just keep adding things and then this case, the top of our stack or the
kylie jue: Way, you're going to pull things off of is going to be the right hand side over here. So when I pop. The first thing off of my stack. I will pop trip, who was the last name that I put on the stack out
kylie jue: If I'm peak. I see nickname then and then when I pop. Again, I pull nickname off. And again, this is something that you can do when you're declaring stacks using this curly bracket notation.
kylie jue: Alright so that was just a very quick overview of the Q AMP stack data structure in general. Now I want to talk about some common patterns when you're actually using using stacks.
kylie jue: So this is both patterns and pitfalls so common areas that will see. So, first there's a so idiom or another word for patterns. First, I want to talk about emptying a stack or a queue.
kylie jue: So take a look at this code for a second. This is what it looks like to empty a queue. So
kylie jue: you'd create your queue here and then this is just a for loop to produce your cue basically adding the numbers one through six in order by looping over them and in queuing them.
kylie jue: And then if you want to fit those numbers, you would say the while loop, which is a common pattern. You'll see for going through the queue. Well, it's not empty, go ahead and DQ an item and then when you're done just finished. So what this will do is it'll print them in order 123456
kylie jue: It looks very similar. When you do the same thing for a stack. You'll notice that the only difference
kylie jue: Is just the names of these functions, right, with stacks you're pushing instead of in queuing you're popping instead of D queuing, and then you print them in the opposite order, right, because the last thing you put in will be the first thing out.
kylie jue: So it's good to see a side by side of these again very similar structures, just with they ordered the data a little bit differently.
kylie jue: The second idiom, which is a little more tricky is how to iterate over these data structures, while potentially also modifying them.
kylie jue: And one of the main things I want you to keep in mind here, which you'll see in the example is that you only want to calculate the size once before you actually do the loop. So what do I mean by that.
kylie jue: So if we look at the queue here. And just to show you the other way of declaring it I've declared it like this. Right off the bat, instead of using the for loop.
kylie jue: And then what I do is I get the queue size using this thought size function. So, both the cues on the stack have this size function which will return in this case.
kylie jue: Six, which is the number of items inside of the queue. And then when I loop I loop from zero to the size which is stored in a variable d queuing. And then what I'm what this program is doing is it's just keeping the even value. So will re in queue. This is doing a mod base or a mod to
kylie jue: And only in queuing the even numbers again. And then when I print at the end I get 246 so I'm iterating again over the stack. Sorry over the queue and then only reason queuing the value if it is even
kylie jue: So what about first step. This is where it looks a little more different. So again, I'm declaring it the same way. And I'm actually going to create this separate stack result.
kylie jue: Because there's a little you'll run into some more problems. If you try to just keep putting something back into the stack. Right.
kylie jue: I think about the fact that okay if I were to do the exact same code on this side. If I just push the value back to the same stamp instead of a separate result. What would happen, I would basically take off the six
kylie jue: And then I would say, oh, it's even. I'm going to put it back on the stack.
kylie jue: And then all I'm doing is I'm going to six times and just DQ it or not to queuing popping and and pushing the same number over and over again, which is just the number six.
kylie jue: And I don't want that. Right, what I wanted. As a result, that only has the even numbers. So instead, what I'm doing is I'm pushing these even numbers to a separate stack called result.
kylie jue: But again, you'll see the parallels here the queuing and popping. They both have the size and then pushing it in queuing, and then you get them in the reverse order in the resulting stack because you're, again, going from the top down.
kylie jue: And then what I was pointing out here is the fact that we in both of these cases are using this variable original size when we're going over our for loop, why don't we just put stack idiom dot size here or Q idiom dot size here.
kylie jue: What this actually does is it will cause you to have a bug. If you do that and the reason for that is as you're removing things from your stack or your queue that size is changing.
kylie jue: And so your for loop condition is going to also be changing as you go. And this is the source of many bugs you would think, oh, I'm actually reducing the code or making it more simple by combining these two lines, but it will actually cause issues here.
kylie jue: So don't do it if you need to iterate over a stacker acute store the size and the variable first. It'll just make your life a lot easier.
kylie jue: And then the second thing is, unlike with cues. You can iterate over a stack without destroying his that previous example shows
kylie jue: So you want to think about when is it beneficial to have a separate stack that I'm populating or to actually make a copy of my original stack and edit the copy as opposed to the original one. If you want to maintain whatever the original source of data was
kylie jue: Yeah. So those are just some common things to keep in mind when you're working with stacks and Q's both similarities and differences between the two.
kylie jue: Right, and then just as a zoom out even more. What are some trade offs between stacks and using other at TS like vectors and grids that we talked about.
kylie jue: In terms of use case, you could probably see that the use cases are pretty different.
kylie jue: But some general like downsides for using stacks and Q's, is that you can't even though the data is ordered right it maintains a very specific order based on how you've put things in or taking things out.
kylie jue: You can't just say, I want to figure out what the third element in my stack or my queue is there's no random access. You can either get the top or the front of the stack or queue or nothing else.
kylie jue: There's also no side effects true for each reversal. So the only way to sort of go through all the elements is to go through the ones that come before it.
kylie jue: And again, this is actually considered a feature because sometimes it allows you to constrain the way people are using your data rather than allowing them to just access anywhere in the vector. If you were to use something that had like a vector capabilities.
kylie jue: But related Lee, there's no easy way to just search through a cure stack for something to say like, is this contained in my queue or stuck. You have to go through everything.
kylie jue: So again, benefits useful for problems that specifically will use this last in first out or first in first out model. And it actually will constrain your data.
kylie jue: In that way, and then it's also again will learn about arrays later in the quarter, but it's very easy to build these from arrays, so that these facts and cues are actually faster than a typical
kylie jue: Vector where you would be able to index into them.
kylie jue: And then this is just a side note, specifically for stacks.
kylie jue: But just some food for thought where would you have the top of the stack be if you're creating one with a vector. And why do you think that would be fast. So just give you a little bit of an intuition of how it's possible for these to be fast.
kylie jue: Even though, realistically, we're using an array underneath, rather than a vector.
kylie jue: Alright, so before we jump into that activity. Are there any questions on cues versus stacks and the activity is going to ask you to think about
kylie jue: Where we're going to use these in real life. So if that's your question, hold it for the end of the activity. But any questions about specifics of using keys and stacks.
kylie jue: Anything in the chat mic. Okay.
kylie jue: Cool. Great. So let's go ahead. We have a perfect amount of time to do this, we're going to reopen breakout rooms and do this activity with ADT. So how is this going to work.
kylie jue: So you've learned about for at so far vectors grids queues and stacks.
kylie jue: And these are different things in the real world use abstract data structures. And what I want you to do is think about which one of these four would you use for the given task on the right.
kylie jue: And if you open up the workspace. You can either discuss it or open the workspace. But the question is here and the T's dot txt file again.
kylie jue: And these are the use cases, these are the back the data structures that you can use. So we're going to reopen the workspaces ask you to think about it.
kylie jue: Probably actually for three minutes instead of five, so we can come back for one minute at the end and discuss. So Nick, if you could open up those rooms already done. Great.
kylie jue: Alright folks are in those rooms and discussing, I will talk a little bit through these for the folks watching from home, who are not live
kylie jue: So again, we've learned about four ordered data structures vectors grids cues and stacks and what we're discussing is for each of these use cases which at do you think would be best suited for the job and why
kylie jue: So the first one is the Undo button in a text editor. The second is jobs for admitted to a printer that can also be cancelled. The third is layer request. So the office hours. Q that we use.
kylie jue: And then we have browsing history Google Spreadsheets and call centers where they handle calls by the next available agent.
kylie jue: And I am going to actually talk about these when the whole group comes back as well. So I might, if you are watching this at home. I encourage you to pause the video and think about these yourself and then you can forward to where we start talking again as a group.
Questions.
Yeah. One last
One.
Okay.
kylie jue: Maybe it like
Bring them back. Okay.
Cool.
Thomas Tao Hale: Sweet. Nice.
kylie jue: Maybe it's just the Wi Fi. Maybe it's your computer.
kylie jue: All right, as people are trickling back. And let's go ahead and start talking about what you discussed. So the first one and undo button in a text editor. So this one is
kylie jue: If you think about it, right, you only ever care about what the last thing you did was so this is a great example of where a stack.
brianzhg@stanford.edu: Would be used
kylie jue: Right, so you have a stack of the last operations you did and you just pop off the last one. If you want to undo it and then you can keep undoing changes like that.
kylie jue: Job submitted to a printer that can also be canceled. This one is tricky because you often hear about the printing jobs as being cute.
kylie jue: So you can think about this one as a queue. But the other. The key thing here is sort of that can be cancel if you want to be able to cancel any sort of job. Remember that with a que, you can't just index into any job.
kylie jue: So in this case, what you would actually want to use is probably a vector.
kylie jue: But if you talked about the possibility of using a queue here at totally makes sense as well, but they can be cancelled part where you want to choose random ones that have been cute already, you would need a vector for
kylie jue: The layer request, you probably this one is actually called a layer Q, we really only process them in order. So layer requests are in the queue.
kylie jue: Your browsing history. This one is actually very similar to the Undo button in a text editor, where if you're hitting the back button that's actually using a stack for the last pages that you visited
kylie jue: But if you're looking at that, like giant list of history, maybe in a separate tab that shows everything
kylie jue: That's probably more likely a vector where you can then click into the different one. So depending on the browser and where you're looking. It actually is implemented in different ways.
kylie jue: Google Spreadsheets is a grid because it's spreadsheet and then call centers are keeps your call be handled by the next available agent. They want you to go in order for that would be pretty bad customer service.
kylie jue: Alright, so hopefully you got a chance to discuss those in your groups and then I just want to do a very, I know we're running a little overtime. So fastest summary so far, but we can
kylie jue: So we've talked about ordered at TS those with accessible indices on factors and grids, those without where you can't access elements by index or cues and stacks.
kylie jue: The traits and the differences here or that you can easily search through the elements when you can access the indices
kylie jue: And verses here it constraints, the way you insert an access data, but they can be more efficient. And that's the key thing for solving specific problems that are good for this lipo and FICO structure.
kylie jue: So that's what you really want to think about when you're deciding what to use what's next tomorrow I'm going to talk about an order data structures sets and maps.
kylie jue: And then that will be the close to our ADT section of the class. So, all right, we'll stick around for questions. But thank you all for coming today.